Finding Aid for Anthony Wojsowski papers, 1921-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Anthony Wojsowski papers 1921-1978 1920s-1930s, and 1950s.
Wojsowski, Anthony.
0.6 linear feet, 1 oversize volume, and 1 oversize folder
2010081 Aa 2; Ac
Papers of Anthony Wojsowski, Socialist Party candidate for Congress from the 1st Michigan District in 1948, and General Secretary of Polish-American Labor Council; files relating to the Polish-American Labor Council, the Polish Mechanics Company, and other Polish-American organizations.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Benjamin Stanczyk (donor no. 4196 ) in 2010.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Anthony Wojsowski was also the General Secretary of Polish-American Labor Council. He unsuccessfully ran for the Michigan House of Representative from the 1st Congressional District in 1948 (Democrat George G. Sadowski won the election). Wojsowski was actively involved with the Polish Mechanics Company, Inc., Michigan and Midwest chapters of the Committee for the Protection of Foreign Born, and other Michigan Polish and political organizations.
The collection documents the history and of the Polish-American Labor Council and Polish Mechanics Company, Inc., and other Polish American organizations, as well Anthony Wojsowski's activities.
Subjects:
American Committee for the Protection of the Foreign Born.; Polish-American Labor Council.; Polish Americans--Michigan.; Polish Mechanics Company, Inc.; Sadowski, George Gregory, 1903-1961.; Wojsowski, Anthony.
Contributors:
American Committee for the Protection of the Foreign Born.
- Organizational files
  The Organizational files series contains correspondence, calendars of events, meeting announcements, addresses, financial documentation, as well as texts of essays and articles on historical and political subjects, newsletters and other printed material of several organizations with which Wojsowski has been involved: the Polish-American Labor Council, the Polish People's University (Polski Uniwesytet Ludowy), Michigan, Midwest, and out of state chapters of the Committee for the Protection of Foreign Born.
  - Polish-American Labor Council, 1942-1976, undated (Box 1)
  - Polski Uniwersytet Ludowy (Polish People's University), 1953-1954, 1958 undated (Box 1)
  - Committee for the Protection of Foreign Born, Midwest and Michigan chapters, 1951, 1958-1959, undated (Box 1)
  - Committee for the Protection of Foreign Born, out of state chapters, 1940, 1954-1956, 1958-1959, undated (Box 1)
- Polish Mechanics Company, Inc.
  The Polish Mechanics Company, Inc. series contains by-laws, correspondence, financial, and legal documentation, as well as lists of names of stockholders.
  - Incorporation and by-laws, 1923 undated (Box 1)
  - Protocols of meetings, 1923-1926, 1933, 1935, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1922-19251937-1938 (Box 1)
  - Legal documents, 1923-1925, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Financial documents, 1923-1926, 1933-1938 (Box 1)
  - Authorizations, 1921, 1923-1924, 1935, 1948-1949, 1954, 1956 undated (Box 1)
  - Stockholders, undated, 3 folders). (Box 1)
  - General ledger, 1920-1923, 1 volume (Volume 1)
  - Commemorative album, undated (Box 1)
- Other materials
  The Other materials series contains Wojsowski's personal files relating to Wojsowski's U.S. legal status and travel abroad, dated 1924-1925. George G. Sadowski 78th U.S. Congress election campaign materials, dated mostly 1942, include press releases and endorsements by labor organizations. Included here are speeches and transcripts of interviews from the electoral campaigns of the Communist party congressional candidate Thomas X. Dombrowski, dated mostly 1944 and 1946. Also included here miscellaneous printed materials, outsize printed materials, and newspaper clippings dating between 1941 and 1978.
  - Personal files, 1924-1925, undated (Box 1)
  - George G. Sadowski campaign, 1942, undated (Box 1)
  - Thomas X. Dombrowski campaign, 1944-1946, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1945-1947, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous printed materials, 1945, 1950, 1953, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1941, 1945, 1949-1950, 1952-1953, 1957, 1959-1960, 1963 undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous printed materials, 1941, 1944, 1948-1951, 1969, 1976, 1978 (Folder 1)